Guide to the Davies/Scroggie Collection of Canadian Fur Trade Documents
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Davies/Scroggie collection of Canadian fur trade documents
1724-1856
WA MSS S-2357
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
The collection consists of printed contracts completed in manuscript between Canadian voyageurs and their outfitters (1801-1821) and other documents relating to the Canadian fur trade, including correspondence, financial papers, and legal documents (1724-1856). Outfitters include M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co., M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co., and the American Fur Company. Destinations include Michilimackinac, Grand Portage, Rainy Lake, Fort William, and "Posts of the Northwest in Upper Canada."
Davies, Grant, 1947-
Davies, Carole-Ann Scroggie, 1949-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Grant Davies, 1999-2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printed contracts completed in manuscript between Canadian voyageurs and their outfitters (1801-1821) and other documents relating to the Canadian fur trade, including correspondence, financial papers, and legal documents (1724-1856). Outfitters include M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co., M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co., and the American Fur Company. Destinations include Michilimackinac, Grand Portage, Rainy Lake, Fort William, and "Posts of the Northwest in Upper Canada."
Appendix: List of Voyageur Contracts (1999 Acquisition)
1.
Outfitter William W. Matthews (agent for) American Fur Co.
Voyageur Jos. Carpentier of Faubourg St. Antoine
Place & date Montreal, 21 March 1818
Destination [Michilimackinac, but not stated]
Position milieu
Payment 400 livres per annum
Length of contract three years
Signatures cross
Observations 2 shirts in his outfit rather than the usual 4; received 6 piastres upon signing, another 4 when leaving
Comments This contract is for the American Fur Company (J.J. Astor's),with Matthews acting as agent
Lande type GN18(h)
2.
Outfitter William W. Matthews (agent for) American Fur Co.
Voyageur Louis Osier and Charles Wilburner of Beaucherville (Boucherville)
Place & date Montreal, 21 March 1818
Destination [Michilimackinac, but not stated]
Position milieu
Payment 500 livres per annum
Length of contract three years
Signatures two crosses
Observations received 6 piastres upon signing, another 4 when leaving
Comments This contract is for the American Fur Company (J.J. Astor's), with Matthews acting as agent; highly unusual in that thecontract is for two voyageurs rather than two individual contracts
Lande type GN18(h)
3.
Outfitter William W. Matthews (agent for) American Fur Co.
Voyageur Pierre Rocheleau of Côte des Neiges
Place & date Montreal, 23 March 1818
Destination [Michilimackinac, but not stated]
Position bowsman
Payment 700 livres per annum
Length of contract three years
Signatures cross
Observations will have a 'carrot' of tobacco added to the usual equipment;received 10 piastres upon signing, another 15 when leaving
Comments This contract is for the American Fur Company (J.J. Astor's), with Matthews acting as agent
Lande type GN18(h)
4.
Outfitter William W. Matthews (agent for) American Fur Co.
Voyageur Joseph McFarlane of Lachine
Place & date Montreal, 24 March 1818
Destination [Michilimackinac, but not stated]
Position milieu
Payment 600 livres per annum
Length of contract three years
Signatures cross
Observations will receive same outfit as he received on his previous trip; received 10 piastres upon signing, another 5 when leaving
Comments This contract is for the American Fur Company (J.J. Astor's), with Matthews acting as agent
Lande type GN18(h)
5.
Outfitter David Mitchell Jr.
Voyageur Jacques Sené of Montreal
Place & date Montreal, 7 April 1806
Destination Michilimackinac and Southern (U.S.) trading posts
Position milieu
Payment 550 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Jacques Sené
Observations will receive double the usual equipment; work as a mason, his trade, when so requested; receives 10 piastres on account and will receive another 4 piastres when leaving
Comments David Mitchell, b. ca. 1750, d. 1832, fur-trader, was a member of the Beaver Club of Montreal
Lande type GN06(h)
6.
Outfitter Forsyth, Richardson & Co.
Voyageur Jean Tremblie (Tremblay) of St. Regis
Place & date Montreal, 18 April 1806
Destination Michilimackinac and posts depending upon Michilimackinac
Position milieu
Payment 400 livres the first, 450 for the second year
Length of contract two years
Signatures mark of Jean Tremblie
Observations received double the usual equipment, 1 piastre on account, will receive 4 piastres when leaving, and 11 piastres have to be paid to André Bourdeau (a debt) from his wages
Comment This contract is for the Michilimackinac Company. After theamalgamation of the XY Company with the NWC late 1804, Forsyth, Richardson & Co. entered into the partnership of the Michilimackinac Co. In 1807 both partners were granted membership in the Beaver Club
Lande type GN05(h)
7.
Outfitter Joseph Faniant
Voyageur Alexis Courchêne, resident of Chenail du Nord
Place & date Chenail du Nord, 5 July 1803
Destination Rainy Lake and Fort Kaministiguia
Position bowsman
Payment 142 livres
Length of contract return trip, without wintering
Signatures marks of Alexis Courchêne and of Joseph Faniant
Observations payment made entirely in advance; will be responsible for reimbursing the money if he does not leave when required to do so
Comments on printed form of M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co., Faniant (Fainant, Fainante), agent of the NW Co. here hires a voyageur for his own services. Faniant is mentioned as a foreman in the trade as far back as 1783 with Waddin in the Peter Pond affair and later by Joseph Frobisher in a 1791 letter to Simon M'Tavish
Lande type MF02
8.
Outfitter Joseph Faniant (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur François Lagarde, of St-Ours
Place & date Berthier, 6 January 1801
Destination Fort des Prairies (Red River)
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 750 livres the first year, afterwards the wages of the trading post where he will be
Length of contract three years
Signatures mark of François Lagarde, signatures of [witnesses] Antoine-Amable Piet, Joseph C. Duvernay jr., and notary Maurice L.D. de Glandons
Observations the voyageur receives double the usual equipment upon his departure, will carry four packs on the return trip, and receives 72 livres on account
Comments unusual in that it is signed by the voyageur, the notary andtwo witnesses
Lande type MF99(h) (Canadian imprint before 1800)
9.
Outfitter Joseph Faniant (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Joseph Pillon (Pilon), of Dautrai
Place & date Berthier, 22 January 1801
Destination Grand Portage
Position second in the brigade of Faniant
Payment blanks not filled in [?]
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Joseph Pilon, signatures of [witnesses] Antoine-Amable Piet, and Joseph C. Duvernay jr.
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, andreceives 120 livres on account
Comments unusual in that it is also signed by two witnesses; also thatit stipulates the voyageur will be part of Faniant's canoe (canot de maître?)
Lande type MF99 (Canadian imprint before 1800)
10.
Outfitter Louis Belair for Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Charles Belmard (Bellemare) of Rivière-du-Loup
Place & date Masquinongé, 21 March 1801
Destination Northern posts
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Jean-Baptiste Gagnon, signatures of Louis and Joseph Belair, as well as notary Maurice L. D. deGlandons
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives double the usual equipment; no money is given on account
Comments unusual in that it is signed by both parties as well as the notary
Lande type MF00(h)
11.
Outfitter Louis Belair for Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jean-Baptiste Gagnon of Rivière-du-Loup
Place & date Masquinongé, 21 March 1801
Destination Grand Portage
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Jean-Baptiste Gagnon, signatures of Louis and Joseph Belair, as well as notary Maurice L. D. deGlandons
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, and receives double the usual equipment and 72 livres on account
Comments unusual in that it is signed by both parties as well as thenotary.
Lande type MF00(h)
12.
Outfitter Louis Belair for Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jacques Roy, of Rivière-du-Loup
Place & date Masquinongé, 21 March 1801
Destination Grand Portage
Position steersman
Payment 400 livres, will receive an extra 200 livres if required toproceed to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Jacques Roy, signatures of Louis and Joseph Belair, as well as notary Maurice L. D. deGlandons
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, and receives 240 livres on account
Comment unusual in that it is signed by both parties as well as the notary. Jean-Marie Boucher enjoyed a long and activelife in the fur trade and eventually established a house and store right outside the compound at Fort William where he wasrenowned for his ability to induce the voyageurs to part with their hard-earned funds and even extended credit to them. His house is a permanent part of any plan illustratingthe layout of Old Fort William. (Lande, p. 48).
Lande type MF00
13.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Louis LeClerc, cabinet maker, of Rivière-du-Loup
Place & date Rivière-du-Loup, 6 April 1801
Destination Northern posts, except Nipigon and Temiscaming
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures signatures of Lesieur [witness?] and Ls. Le Claire
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip,receives double the usual equipment; and 144 livres onaccount
Comments unusual in that it is signed by the voyageur, rather thanwith his mark. The man is also a tradesman, but thecontract makes no mention that he will be required to workin his trade at the posts
Lande type MF00(h)
14.
Outfitter Louis Belair for Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Samuel Wells of Masquinongé
Place & date Masquinongé, 6 April 1801
Destination Northern posts
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Samuel Wells, signatures of Joseph and Louis Belair
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip,receives double the usual equipment; and 84 livres on account
Comments unusual in that it is signed by both parties as well as thenotary
Lande type MF00(h)
15.
Outfitter John Gregory of Berthier, agent (not John Gregory, partner for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur André Hallé, of Contrecoeur
Place & date Montreal, 26 November 1801
Destination Northwest and dependencies, except Nipigon
Position "wintering" steersman
Payment 1500 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures Louis Chaboillez, notary
Observations the voyageur will carry six packs on the return trip, receives double the usual equipment; 600 livres on accountand will receive another 200 livres on account the followingautumn (prior to departure). Voyageurs usually carried two packs of 90 pounds per trip; mention is made in the contract when the voyageur is willing to carry four packs of fur, butthis is the first contract where the voyageur agrees to carrysix packs (or 540 lbs!). His wages are also higher than thosefor any other voyageur contract we have ever seen.
Comments listed with "outfit" for 1802, because outfits start in October of preceding year
Lande type MF00(h)
16.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jean-Baptiste Papin, of St-Sulpice
Place & date St-Sulpice, 5 January 1802
Destination Fort des Prairies (Red River)
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment the rate old (experienced) winterers are paid at the post
Length of contract one year
Signatures signatures of Baptiste Papin, and Louis Barbier and Baptist [sic] Ham [?] as witnesses
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives double the usual equipment; and 200 livres on account
Comments unusual in that it is signed by the voyageur
Lande type MF01(h)
17.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Étienne Charron dit DuCharme, of St-Pierre [Sorel]
Place & date Berthier, 20 January 1802
Destination Temiscaming
Position milieu
Payment 350 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Étienne Charron, signatures of Louis Barbier and Baptist [sic] Ham [?] as witnesses
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives the usual equipment; and 120 livres on account
Comments
Lande type MF00
18.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Antoine La Pierre son of Pierre (La Pierre), of St-Cuthbert
Place & date Berthier, 29 April 1802
Destination Northern posts
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 750 livres the first year, afterwards the rate of the post
Length of contract two years
Signatures mark of Antoine La Pierre
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives double the usual equipment; and 12 livres on account
Comments
Lande type MF00(h)
19.
Outfitter Alexis Trempé (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Augustin Roy, of Chatoyer
Place & date Berthier, 29 January 1802
Destination "the Northern limits"
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 750 livres, and afterwards the rate of the post
Length of contract two years
Signatures mark of Augustin Roy, and signatures of Alexis Trempé, as well as Louis Barbier and Baptist [sic] Ham [?] as witnesses
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives the usual equipment; and 24 livres on account
Comments unusual in that it is signed by both parties. "Trempé isa foreman who is later mentioned in reference to the secondFranklin expedition. Peter Warren Dease, in letter of 13 May1825 to Robert McVicar writes telling of how he sent Trempé to Great Bear Lake to prepare for Franklin's arrival there." (Lande, p. 52).
Lande type MF00(h)
20.
Outfitter Frederick Singer (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Joseph Charpentier, of Baie du Febvre
Place & date Baie du Febvre, 24 May 1802
Destination Grand Portage
Position second
Payment 400 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Joseph Charpentier, and signatures of Joseph Le maitre, witness, and Frederick Singer
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives the usual equipment; and 200 livres on account
Comments unusual in that it is signed by both parties.
Lande type MF00
21.
Outfitter Frederick Singer (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Joseph Gauthier, of Baie du Febvre
Place & date St-François, 24 May 1802
Destination Grand Portage
Position milieu
Payment 400 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Joseph Gauthier, and signatures of Joseph Le maitre, as witness, as well as Frederick Singer
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives the usual equipment; 96 livres on account, and willreceive another 154 livres at time of his departure
Comments unusual in that it is signed by both parties. "Singer recruited his men from Lormière and St-François which at that time, as today, was a predominantly Mohawk settlement." (Lande, p. 58).
Lande type MF00
22.
Outfitter Frederick Singer (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Louis Senneville, of Baie du Febvre
Place & date Baie du Febvre, 24 May 1802
Destination Grand Portage
Position milieu
Payment 400 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Louis Senneville, and signatures of Joseph Le Maitre, witness, and Frederick Singer
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives the usual equipment; 96 livres on account and willreceive 154 livres upon his departure
Comments unusual in that it is signed by both parties.
Lande type MF00
23.
Outfitter Frederick Singer (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jean-Baptiste Laurance (Laurence), of Berthier
Place & date Berthier, 25 May 1802
Destination Grand Portage
Position steersman
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Jean-Baptiste Laurence, and signature of Frederick Singer
Observations the voyageur will carry four packs on the return trip, receives the usual equipment; and 400 livres on account
Comments unusual in that it is signed by both parties.
Lande type MF00
24.
Outfitter Régis Lorange of Berthier (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Pierre Ganon (Gagnon) of Machiche
Place & date Machiche, 25 December 1802
Destination Rainy Lake
Position milieu
Payment 450 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Pierre Gagnon, signatures of Claude Laurangé [sic] and Pierre-Joseph Théroux
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and 60 francs on account
Comments unusual because signed by both parties. "The last summer at Grand Portage was in 1802. Since the historic depot was located in American territory about 20 miles south of the border on the shore of lake Superior, it was ultimately given up asAmerican territory following the dictates of Jay's Treaty of 1794. As a matter of fact, a few men and a clerk remained stationed there for several years thereafter but more as a point of dissuasion to the XY rivals than as a depot and point of entry to the portage." (Lande, p. 60)
Lande type MF03 (not illustrated)
25.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Étienne Charron dit Ducharme of Berthier
Place & date Berthier, 8 October 1803
Destination Grand Portage
Position steersman
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Étienne Charron
Observations the voyageur will carry 4 packs on the return trip, receives the usual equipment and 180 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered). It is also interesting to note that the voyageur was still sent to Grand Portage (see comment to entry above)
Lande type MF00
26.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Louis Godon (Godoin?) of Ste-Geneviève de Batiscan
Place & date Berthier, 21 October 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position steersman
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract return trip during the year 1805, since he is already hired for the outfit of 1804
Signatures mark of Louis Godon; signature of jaen mair bouché [sic]
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and has received 200 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered). Unusual (for fairly obvious reasons) in that it bears the signature of Jean-Marie Boucher, the agent.
Lande type MF02
27.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Charles Chrétien of Rivière-du-Loup
Place & date Berthier, 3 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres for the first year, afterwards the rate of the post where he will be
Length of contract three years
Signatures marks of Charles Chrétien and Jean Bruno, his tutor
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and has received 24 livres on account; his tutor will receive 100 livres upon Chrétien's departure
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered). Unusual because this contract is for a minor, and that his tutor is to receive part of his wages
Lande type MF03(h) (not illustrated)
28.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur François Éno dit Canada of Berthier
Place & date Berthier, 9 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position second steersman on the Great River, and bowsman inland
Payment 600 livres (or 500, corrected in ink, but not clear from text)
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of François Éno
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and has received 180 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02
29.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur François Charron dit Ducharme jr. of St-Pierre de Berthier
Place & date Berthier, 12 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position milieu
Payment 450 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of François Charron
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and has received 15 piastres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02
30.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Joseph Matte, Jr. of Berthier
Place & date Berthier, 12 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 650 livres for the first year, second and third year the rate of the post
Length of contract three years
Signatures mark of Joseph Matte
Observations the voyageur receives double the usual equipment of a winterer and has received 48 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02(h)
31.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Joseph Sanssoussy (Sanssouci) of Ile Dupas
Place & date Berthier, 20 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position "bout de canot" (instead of the usual term, gouvernail, i.e. steersman)
Payment 700 livres and if rates increase he will receive the difference
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Joseph Sanssouci
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and 300 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered). See also entrybelow for contract of same date made out to his relative, Louis Sanssouci. Unusual in that it stipulates a possible increase of salary if conditions change.
Lande type MF02
32.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Louis Sanscousy (Sanssouci) of Ile Dupas
Place & date Berthier, 20 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position milieu
Payment 450 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Louis Sanssouci
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and 100 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered).
Lande type MF02
33.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur François Dussault of Ile St-Ignace
Place & date Berthier, 24 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position second on the Great River, and milieu inland
Payment 500 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of François Dussault
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and 150 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02
34.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jean-Baptiste Latour of Ile St-Ignace
Place & date Berthier, 24 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position second on the Great River, and milieu inland
Payment 500 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Jean-Baptiste Latour
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and 150 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02
35.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Pierre Vilandré son of Antoine, of parish of St-Esprit, Berthier
Place & date Berthier, 25 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position milieu
Payment 450 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Pierre Vilandré
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and 150 livres on account, and will receive no more until his return
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02
36.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.